<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Olga Doronina</title><link>https://olgadoronina.github.io/author/olga-doronina/</link><atom:link href="https://olgadoronina.github.io/author/olga-doronina/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>Olga Doronina</description><generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>©</copyright><image><url>https://olgadoronina.github.io/author/olga-doronina/avatar_huba3fdfcdf06e8a6d45e7ebabe76ba20d_2232883_270x270_fill_q90_lanczos_center.jpg</url><title>Olga Doronina</title><link>https://olgadoronina.github.io/author/olga-doronina/</link></image><item><title>Parameter Estimation for Reynolds-Averaged Navier--Stokes Models Using Approximate Bayesian Computation</title><link>https://olgadoronina.github.io/publication/2021_abc_rans/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://olgadoronina.github.io/publication/2021_abc_rans/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Flow parameter estimation using laser absorption spectroscopy and approximate Bayesian computation</title><link>https://olgadoronina.github.io/publication/2021_abc_spectroscopy/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://olgadoronina.github.io/publication/2021_abc_spectroscopy/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Parameter Estimation for Subgrid-Scale Models Using Markov Chain Monte Carlo Approximate Bayesian Computation</title><link>https://olgadoronina.github.io/publication/2020_abc_les/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://olgadoronina.github.io/publication/2020_abc_les/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Approximate Bayesian Computation for Parameter Estimation in RANS Turbulence Models</title><link>https://olgadoronina.github.io/talk/aps_2019/</link><pubDate>Tue, 26 Nov 2019 08:24:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://olgadoronina.github.io/talk/aps_2019/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Simulating Aerodynamics of a Moving Body Specified by Immersed Boundaries on Dynamically Adaptive Unstructured Meshes</title><link>https://olgadoronina.github.io/publication/2019_moving_mesh/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://olgadoronina.github.io/publication/2019_moving_mesh/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Autonomic Closure for Turbulent Flows Using Approximate Bayesian Computation</title><link>https://olgadoronina.github.io/publication/2018_autonomic_abc/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://olgadoronina.github.io/publication/2018_autonomic_abc/</guid><description>&lt;p>Autonomic closure is a new technique for achieving physically accurate adaptive closure
of coarse-grained turbulent flow governing equations, such as those solved in large eddy simulations (LES). Although autonomic closure has been shown in recent a priori tests to more
accurately represent unclosed terms than do dynamic versions of traditional LES models, the
optimization step used in the approach introduces large matrices that must be inverted, resulting in high memory usage. In order to reduce memory requirements, here we propose the use
of approximate Bayesian computation (ABC) in place of the optimization step, thereby yielding
an autonomic closure implementation that trades memory-intensive for processor-intensive
computations. These computations can be handled by co-processors such as general purpose
graphical processing units that are becoming increasingly available on petascale supercomputers. In this paper, we outline the formulation of ABC-enabled autonomic closure and present
initial results demonstrating the accuracy of the approach.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Numerical study of acoustic radiation dynamics of a Rankine vortex</title><link>https://olgadoronina.github.io/publication/2016_vortex/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Jun 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://olgadoronina.github.io/publication/2016_vortex/</guid><description>&lt;p>The paper investigates the problem of sound radiation by a perturbed Rankine vortex, which is important for understanding the nature of vortex flows and acoustic radiation generated by them. This problem is difficult to simulate numerically due to the sharp boundary between the vortex and potential flows.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We consider quadrupole and higher mode radiation as well as the dynamics of tonal acoustic radiation generated by a perturbed vortex with a gradual transition to lower harmonics. In addition, we consider the transition of a stationary Rankine vortex to a perturbed state under small external perturbation.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The mathematical description of the problem is based on Euler equations. Numerical simulation is performed on unstructured grids using a high accuracy EBR (Edge Based Reconstruction) scheme.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Thus, our paper aims to study the generation of acoustic radiation by a perturbed Rankine vortex. In addition, we verify the possibility of correct numerical simulation for complex fundamental vortex dynamics problems. In particular, the applicability of high accuracy numerical algorithms on unstructured grids to simulate such problems.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Numerical simulation of acoustic waves scattering by isolated vortex structures</title><link>https://olgadoronina.github.io/publication/2013_vortex/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Mar 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://olgadoronina.github.io/publication/2013_vortex/</guid><description>&lt;p>The problem of sound scattering by an isolated vortex is not only interesting to study, but it is also fundamental for understanding the interaction between acoustic waves and vortex flow, including the process of sound generation by turbulence. Understanding the sound generation process is essential for many practical applications.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>When turbulence is represented by a distribution of localized vortices with certain static properties, the acoustic field scattered by such a flow is a superposition of scattered acoustic fields from each vortex. Therefore, the description of the elementary event of sound scattering sound by an isolated vortex can be used to predict the impact of turbulence on the acoustic field.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>For the numerical simulation of this problem, we used a linear approximation of the mathematical model. This approximation is quite realistic because it reveals the main properties of the studied phenomena. Thus, we modeled the problem using a system of linearized Euler equations, in which a vortex is defined as a background field.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>One of the goals of this study was to test the ability of the EBR (Edge-Based Reconstruction) numerical scheme to model considered problems on unstructured grids and to assess its accuracy and efficiency compared to other approaches. Thus, we used the EBR scheme (the fifth-order scheme based on the quasi-one-dimensional reconstruction), implemented in a highly parallel research code NOISEtte (KIAM RAS).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>First, we showed the simulation results of the plane acoustic wave scattering by isentropic Gaussian-core vortex with a constant circulation velocity. We also provided the study of grid convergence to the benchmark solution. Besides Cartesian grids, we used quasi-uniform unstructured triangular grids and demonstrated that the results are almost identical for the same number of grid points.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We also consider the problem of the cylindrical point source acoustic wave scattering by the Rankine vortex. We perform simulations on unstructured grids and compare the results of different numerical approaches: a finite-volume approach (NOISEtte EBR), a finite element approach (Actran DGM), and a finite-difference (Cabaret scheme).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The results confirm that NOISEtte and its numerical method can be successfully used to simulate the interaction between acoustic waves and vortex structures.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Using ABC for turbulence model calibration</title><link>https://olgadoronina.github.io/project/abc_turbulence_modeling/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://olgadoronina.github.io/project/abc_turbulence_modeling/</guid><description>&lt;p>Real-world turbulent flows are challenging to simulate due to the high computational cost of resolving all their relevant spatial and temporal scales. There are two common approaches to reduce the cost of such simulations:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Large_eddy_simulation" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Large-Eddy Simulations (LES)&lt;/a>, which directly resolve turbulence on large scales and use subgrid-scale (SGS) models to represent small-scale physics&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Reynolds-averaged_Navier%E2%80%93Stokes_equations" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Reynolds averaged Navier-Stokes (RANS)&lt;/a> approaches, which resolve only averaged quantities and model turbulent fluctuations&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>However, there is no universally accurate turbulence model in either of these approaches. Besides that, all models rely on empirical coefficients that we must calibrate for different flows and geometries.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We suggest using the
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Approximate_Bayesian_computation" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Approximate Bayesian Computation (ABC)&lt;/a> methods, also known as likelihood-free methods. ABC is a data-driven approach, which uses experimental or higher fidelity data to approximate the probability distribution of model parameters. As a result, we can choose model parameters and quantify their uncertainty based on (or even sample from) this estimated probability distribution.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>ABC is based on the Bayesian approach but does not require knowing the analytical expression for a likelihood function. The primary advantages of ABC are its lower cost relative to full Bayesian methods and its flexibility in parameter estimation for complex models, e.g., turbulence models, which consist of partial differential equations.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We created a framework called
&lt;a href="https://github.com/olgadoronina/ABC_MCMC" target="_blank" rel="noopener">TurbABC&lt;/a> for turbulent model parameters estimation. TurbABC combines ABC with Markov chain Monte Carlo (MCMC) sampling, an adaptive proposal, and calibration steps to accelerate the parameter estimation process. We demonstrate the efficiency and effectiveness of TurbABC by estimating parameters of:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>nonlinear SGS closures using reference data from direct numerical simulations of homogeneous isotropic turbulence&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>nonequilibrium anisotropy RANS closure in homogeneous turbulent flow with rapidly changing strain tensor&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>RANS model parameters estimation in inhomogeneous turbulent flow (axisymmetric transonic bump)&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul></description></item></channel></rss>