<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>ABC | Olga Doronina</title><link>https://olgadoronina.github.io/tag/abc/</link><atom:link href="https://olgadoronina.github.io/tag/abc/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>ABC</description><generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>©</copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 26 Nov 2019 08:24:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://olgadoronina.github.io/images/icon_hu1fc3393be1206faf735b323c1b5cba8f_24222_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url><title>ABC</title><link>https://olgadoronina.github.io/tag/abc/</link></image><item><title>Approximate Bayesian Computation for Parameter Estimation in RANS Turbulence Models</title><link>https://olgadoronina.github.io/talk/aps_2019/</link><pubDate>Tue, 26 Nov 2019 08:24:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://olgadoronina.github.io/talk/aps_2019/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Autonomic Closure for Turbulent Flows Using Approximate Bayesian Computation</title><link>https://olgadoronina.github.io/publication/2018_autonomic_abc/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://olgadoronina.github.io/publication/2018_autonomic_abc/</guid><description>&lt;p>Autonomic closure is a new technique for achieving physically accurate adaptive closure
of coarse-grained turbulent flow governing equations, such as those solved in large eddy simulations (LES). Although autonomic closure has been shown in recent a priori tests to more
accurately represent unclosed terms than do dynamic versions of traditional LES models, the
optimization step used in the approach introduces large matrices that must be inverted, resulting in high memory usage. In order to reduce memory requirements, here we propose the use
of approximate Bayesian computation (ABC) in place of the optimization step, thereby yielding
an autonomic closure implementation that trades memory-intensive for processor-intensive
computations. These computations can be handled by co-processors such as general purpose
graphical processing units that are becoming increasingly available on petascale supercomputers. In this paper, we outline the formulation of ABC-enabled autonomic closure and present
initial results demonstrating the accuracy of the approach.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Using ABC for turbulence model calibration</title><link>https://olgadoronina.github.io/project/abc_turbulence_modeling/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://olgadoronina.github.io/project/abc_turbulence_modeling/</guid><description>&lt;p>Real-world turbulent flows are challenging to simulate due to the high computational cost of resolving all their relevant spatial and temporal scales. There are two common approaches to reduce the cost of such simulations:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Large_eddy_simulation" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Large-Eddy Simulations (LES)&lt;/a>, which directly resolve turbulence on large scales and use subgrid-scale (SGS) models to represent small-scale physics&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Reynolds-averaged_Navier%E2%80%93Stokes_equations" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Reynolds averaged Navier-Stokes (RANS)&lt;/a> approaches, which resolve only averaged quantities and model turbulent fluctuations&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>However, there is no universally accurate turbulence model in either of these approaches. Besides that, all models rely on empirical coefficients that we must calibrate for different flows and geometries.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We suggest using the
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Approximate_Bayesian_computation" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Approximate Bayesian Computation (ABC)&lt;/a> methods, also known as likelihood-free methods. ABC is a data-driven approach, which uses experimental or higher fidelity data to approximate the probability distribution of model parameters. As a result, we can choose model parameters and quantify their uncertainty based on (or even sample from) this estimated probability distribution.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>ABC is based on the Bayesian approach but does not require knowing the analytical expression for a likelihood function. The primary advantages of ABC are its lower cost relative to full Bayesian methods and its flexibility in parameter estimation for complex models, e.g., turbulence models, which consist of partial differential equations.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We created a framework called
&lt;a href="https://github.com/olgadoronina/ABC_MCMC" target="_blank" rel="noopener">TurbABC&lt;/a> for turbulent model parameters estimation. TurbABC combines ABC with Markov chain Monte Carlo (MCMC) sampling, an adaptive proposal, and calibration steps to accelerate the parameter estimation process. We demonstrate the efficiency and effectiveness of TurbABC by estimating parameters of:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>nonlinear SGS closures using reference data from direct numerical simulations of homogeneous isotropic turbulence&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>nonequilibrium anisotropy RANS closure in homogeneous turbulent flow with rapidly changing strain tensor&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>RANS model parameters estimation in inhomogeneous turbulent flow (axisymmetric transonic bump)&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul></description></item></channel></rss>